<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" packageId="knb_lter_ble.1.1." system="knb" xsi:schemaLocation="eml://ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.1.1 http://nis.lternet.edu/schemas/EML/eml-2.1.1/eml.xsd">
  <access system="https://pasta.lternet.edu" scope="document" order="allowFirst" authSystem="https://pasta.lternet.edu/authentication">
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=BLE,o=LTER,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>uid=your_user_id,dc=ecoinformatics,dc=org</principal>
      <permission>all</permission>
    </allow>
    <allow>
      <principal>public</principal>
      <permission>read</permission>
    </allow>
  </access>
  <dataset>
    <alternateIdentifier>knb_lter_ble.1.1</alternateIdentifier>
    <shortName>NA</shortName>
    <title>giant kelp</title>
    <creator>
      <organizationName>UTA</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>UTA</deliveryPoint>
        <city>A</city>
        <administrativeArea>TX</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>78555</postalCode>
        <country>US</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>wow@dot.com</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>Jay</givenName>
        <surName>Doe</surName>
      </individualName>
      <electronicMailAddress>wow@dot.com</electronicMailAddress>
    </creator>
    <pubDate>NA</pubDate>
    <language>English</language>
    <abstract>
      <para>
  The Santa Barbara Channel Marine Biodiversity Observation Network
  (SBCMBON) tracks long-term patterns in species abundance and
  diversity. This dataset contains cover of kelp forest sessile
  invertebrates, understory macroalgae, and substrate types by
  integrating data from four contributing projects working in the kelp
  forests of the Santa Barbara Channel, USA. Divers collect data on
  using either uniform point contact (UPC) or random point contact (RPC)
  methods.
</para>
      <para>
  The four contributing projects are two research projects: The Santa
  Barbara Coastal LTER (SBC LTER) and the Partnership for
  Interdisciplinary Studies of Coastal Oceans (PISCO), and the kelp
  forest monitoring program of the Santa Barbara Channel National Park,
  and the San Nicolas Island monitoring program supported by USGS.
  Together, these projects have recorded data for more than 200 species
  at approximately 100 sites on both the mainland coast and on the Santa
  Barbara Channel Islands. Sampling began in 1982 and is ongoing.
</para>
      <para>
  Percent cover is recorded for taxa where individuals cannot be
  counted. Cover can be calculated from the data here as the fraction of
  total points at which the taxon was present x 100. With UPC and RPC,
  multiple species can be recorded at any given point. The total percent
  cover of all species combined using this method can exceed 100%;
  however, the percent cover of any single species cannot exceed 100%.
  See Methods for information on integration and data processing.
</para>
      <para>
  MBON is funded by National Aeronautics and Space Administration
  (NASA), Bureau of Ocean Energy Management (BOEM), and National Oceanic
  and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA).
</para>
      <para>
  For users who are interested in using all or part of this integrated
  datasets, please contact data owners to discuss your research
  interests, citation for the data package, data related issues or any
  other questions. In addition, any manuscript generated using this
  dataset is expected to be sent to the data owners before publication
  so we can be sure the data is used in the proper context and methods
  are reported accurately.:
</para>
      <para>
  Santa Barbara Coastal LTER (LTER): Dan Reed dan.reed@lifesci.ucsb.edu
</para>
      <para>
  Partnership for Interdisciplinary Studies of Coastal Oceans (PISCO):
  Jenn Caselle caselle@ucsb.edu
</para>
      <para>
  Kelp forest monitoring (KFM): David Kushner david_kushner@nps.gov
</para>
      <para>
  San Nicolas Island monitoring (SNI): Kevin Lafferty Klafferty@usgs.gov
</para>
    </abstract>
    <keywordSet>
      <keyword>kelp</keyword>
      <keywordThesaurus>LTER Network Controlled Vocabulary</keywordThesaurus>
    </keywordSet>
    <intellectualRights>
      <para>
  This data package is released under the Creative Commons license
  Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0 , see
  <ulink url="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ulink>).
  This license states that consumers ("Data Users" herein) may
  distribute, adapt, reuse, remix, and build upon this work, as long as
  they give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and
  indicate if changes were made. If redistributed, a Data User may not
  apply additional restrictions or technological measures that prevent
  access.
</para>
      <para>
  The Data User has an ethical obligation to cite the data source
  appropriately in any publication or product that results from its use,
  and notify the data contact or creator. Communication, collaboration,
  or co-authorship (as appropriate) with the creators of this data
  package is encouraged to prevent duplicate research or publication.
  The Data User is urged to contact the authors of these data if any
  questions about methodology or results occur. The Data User should
  realize that these data may be actively used by others for ongoing
  research and that coordination may be necessary to prevent duplication
  or inappropriate use. The Data User should realize that
  misinterpretation may occur if data are used outside of the context of
  the original study. The Data User should be aware that data are
  updated periodically and it is the responsibility of the Data User to
  check for new versions of the data.
</para>
      <para>
  While substantial efforts are made to ensure the accuracy of data and
  associated documentation, complete accuracy of data sets cannot be
  guaranteed. This data package (with its components) is made available
  “as is” and with no warranty of accuracy or fitness for use. The
  creators of this data package and the repository where these data were
  obtained shall not be liable for any damages resulting from
  misinterpretation, use or misuse of the data package or its
  components.
</para>
    </intellectualRights>
    <distribution>
      <online>
        <url function="information">https://ble.lternet.edu</url>
      </online>
    </distribution>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>kel[</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>NA</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>NA</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>NA</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2008-01-08</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2018-02-28</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <organizationName>BLE LTER</organizationName>
      <positionName>Information Manager, Beaufort Lagoon Ecosystems LTER</positionName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>contact address1</deliveryPoint>
        <deliveryPoint>contact address2</deliveryPoint>
        <city>contact  City</city>
        <administrativeArea>contact state</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>78759-7741</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
      <electronicMailAddress>contact@ble.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <onlineUrl>http://ble.lternet.edu</onlineUrl>
    </contact>
    <publisher>
      <organizationName>publisher org</organizationName>
      <address>
        <deliveryPoint>publisher address</deliveryPoint>
        <city>publisher city</city>
        <administrativeArea>publisher state</administrativeArea>
        <postalCode>90210</postalCode>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </publisher>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
  The integrated dataset combines four monitoring projects in the kelp
  forests of the Santa Barbara Channel, USA. The surveying methods, raw
  data, and meta data files for each project can be found online.
</para>
          <para>
  Santa Barbara Coastal LTER (LTER):
  <ulink url="http://sbc.lternet.edu">http://sbc.lternet.edu</ulink>
</para>
          <para>
  Partnership for Interdisciplinary Studies of Coastal Oceans (PISCO):
  <ulink url="http://data.piscoweb.org/">http://data.piscoweb.org/</ulink>
</para>
          <para>
  Kelp forest monitoring (KFM):
  <ulink url="http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E094/245/">http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E094/245/</ulink>
</para>
          <para>
  San Nicolas Island monitoring (SNI):
  <ulink url="http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E094/244/">http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E094/244/</ulink>
</para>
          <para>
  The data integration process includes data cleaning, column
  standardization, species validation, and data merging. The data
  cleaning was processed in seven steps: 1. Select the sites located
  within the Santa Barbara Channel; 2. Separate the biological survey
  data into three categories: fish survey, quad and swath count, and
  benthic cover; 3. Assign survey area to the corresponding record for
  each survey, and calculate the total point count for the benthic cover
  data; 4. Add life stage (adult and juvenile) information to the survey
  record; 5. Calculate plot average in cases where more than one diver
  surveyed each experimental plot (e.g. KFM roving diver fish count); 6.
  Remove redundant rows; 7. Convert date format into: YYYY-MM-DD.
</para>
          <para>
  After the cleaning process, the designated columns (for the integrated
  dataset) were selected and standardized indices were generated for
  site, subsite, transect, replicate plot, and taxon. Species’
  scientific name were run through an online data base
  <ulink url="http://www.marinespecies.org/">http://www.marinespecies.org/</ulink>
  to obtain an authoritative name and taxon information. Finally, the
  standardized-format table from the four projects were merged into one
  csv file for each survey category.
</para>
          <para>
  For researchers who want to use the integrated datasets, there are
  some potential issues/cautions due to the difference among sampling
  methods of these four programs. Please refer to the protocol listed
  below for the details.
</para>
        </description>
        <protocol>
          <distribution>
            <online>
              <url function="download"/>
            </online>
          </distribution>
        </protocol>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <project>
      <title>your lter spelled out</title>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
          <givenName>PI name</givenName>
          <surName>PI surname</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>PI address1</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>PI address2</deliveryPoint>
          <city>PI city</city>
          <administrativeArea>PI state</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>78758</postalCode>
          <country>United States</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">615-867-5309</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>PI@abc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <personnel>
        <individualName>
          <salutation>Dr.</salutation>
          <givenName>Co-PI name</givenName>
          <surName>Co-PI surname</surName>
        </individualName>
        <address>
          <deliveryPoint>Co-PI address1</deliveryPoint>
          <deliveryPoint>Co-PI address2</deliveryPoint>
          <city>Co-PI city</city>
          <administrativeArea>Co-PI state</administrativeArea>
          <postalCode>78758</postalCode>
          <country>United States</country>
        </address>
        <phone phonetype="voice">615-867-5309</phone>
        <electronicMailAddress>Co-PI@abc.edu</electronicMailAddress>
        <role>Co-Principal Investigator</role>
      </personnel>
      <abstract>
        <section>
          <para>Abstract about your LTER site.</para>
        </section>
      </abstract>
      <funding>
        <section>
          <para>BLE is funded by the National Science Foundation under award 123456.</para>
        </section>
      </funding>
    </project>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
